A Guide to the Wilbur C. Hall Papers, 1831-1970; 1981
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Wilbur C. Hall Papers, 1831-1970; 1981
Thomas Balch Library
M 005, OM 019, VC 0043, ART 003
2 cu. ft. (5 boxes, 4 oversize folders; 9 VC folders).
The Wilbur C. Hall Papers consist primarily of materials relating to Wilbur Hall's interest in the history of early America, Virginia, and Loudoun County. There is little material pertaining to his work as an attorney in Leesburg, his career in government, or his personal and family life.
Loudoun County Library Administration and Karen Titus, Leesburg, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Loudoun County Library Administration and Karen Titus, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2012.0025; 2012.0026
Biographical Information
Born in Leesburg, VA on February 7, 1892, Wilbur C. Hall is noted for his career as a lawyer, state legislator, orator, and public figure. Graduating from Washington and Lee School of Law in Lexington, VA in 1915, Hall served in the United States Navy during World War I. In 1918, at the age of 24, he was elected to the Virginia General Assembly and served on the Assembly until 1935. He served as Chairman of the Virginia Conservation Commission from 1935-1939, and authored or sponsored important and influential legislation.
Wilbur Hall also had a legendary career as a lawyer; he was called a "lawyer's lawyer" and "the best prepared lawyer before the bar of any court in Virginia." Hall contributed to the legal profession in numerous ways, being widely cited in case law and also serving as a supporter of Washington and Lee University's law program. He made several sizable gifts to the law school program during his lifetime, including a loan fund for deserving law students, and left the majority of his estate to Washington and Lee University. In 1967 Washington and Lee bestowed an honorary doctorate degree upon him. Hall noted this as being "the happiest moment of my life." Following his death in August 1972, the law school library, which he helped develop, was named Wilbur C. Hall Law Library.
Hall was a founding member of the Rotary Club of Leesburg and belonged to numerous civic and fraternal organizations. As a public figure and noted orator, he was in demand as a speaker and frequently spoke on historical topics. An amateur historian, Hall also contributed to the preservation of historical landmarks and local historic sites. As Chairman of the Virginia Conservation Commission he helped to create a state historic marker program, establishing a number of markers for Loudoun county historic sites, including the site of Revolutionary war figure John Champe. Hall published articles about Champe and other historical topics of interest to him in a variety of journals. While Hall was a popular speaker and contributor to publications, it should be noted that he hired researchers to complete much of his writing and historical inquiries.
Scope and Content
The Wilbur C. Hall Papers consist primarily of materials relating to Wilbur Hall's interest in the history of early America, Virginia, and Loudoun County. There is little material pertaining to his work as an attorney in Leesburg, his career in government, or his personal and family life. The collection is organized into two series.
Series I consists of documents relating to his research into the history of Loudoun County and surrounding areas. The materials are organized alphabetically by subject. The documents include transcripts of speeches he gave on various historical topics to organizations such as the American Legion, Lion's Club, Rotary Club, Ruritan Club, Loudoun County Chamber of Commerce, local historical societies and others. Also included are associated correspondence and research materials, including publications, maps, historical accounts, clippings and notes. Correspondents include: J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. (1898-1986); W. J. Barrow (1904-1967); Armistead L. Boothe (1907-1990); Mary Brackett (Mrs. Scott) Bowen (1887-1974); Omar N. Bradley (1893-1981); Benjamin H. Branch, Jr. (1919-1993); Wiley T. Buchanan, Jr. (1914-1986); Bryan Conrad (1870-1950); Elbert Cox (1906-1993); Cecil B. Dickson (ca. 1899-1986); E. Griffith Dodson (1923-1962); H. J. Eckenrode (1881-1952); Eugenia T. Fairfax (1873-1966); David E. Finley, Jr. (1890-1977); Marshall W Fishwick (1923-2006); Caroline B. Furness (1922-2007); R. K. Gheen (1914-1974); Stilson H. Hall (1893-1981); George P. Hammerly (1921-1984); Huntington Harris (1914-1993); B. Powell Harrison (1911-2000); William J. Heffner (1909-1995); Laurence G. Hoes (1900-1978); George A. Horkan, Jr. (1926-2005); Carlisle H. Humelsine (1915-1989); Eppa Hunton, IV; (1904-1976); Patrick J. Hurley (1883-1963); Asa Moore Janney (ca. 1908-2002); W. Pat Jennings (1919-1994); Aurelia M. (Mrs. Walter T.) Jewell (1900-1992); Marven Jones (1882-1976); George Harrison Sanford King (1914-1985); George C. Marshall (1880-1959); Katherine Marshall (1882-1978); H(erbert) A. Martz (1898-1990); Frank P. Moncure (1889-1969); Benjamin Muse (1898-1986) Millard C. Myers (1883-1975); Lawrence F. O'Brien, Jr. (1917-1990); Carleton Penn (1922-2009); Lucas D. Phillips (1904-1994); Forrest C. Pogue, Jr. (1912-1996); Joseph E. Profitt (1876-1958); W. Griffith Purcell (1912-1983); Jennings Randolph (1902-1998); A. Willis Robertson (1887-1971); Clarence L. Robey (1884-1969); John W. H. Spencer (1919-2011); William B. Spong, Jr. (1920-1997); Stuart Symington (1901-1988); [Dorothy] Ullrich Troubetzkoy (1914-2003); William M. Tuck (1896-1983); Robert Whitehead (1897-1960); and Conrad L. Wirth (1899-1993).
Series II is made up of original nineteenth century documents collected by Wilbur Hall in the course of his historical research. These documents include letters, public notices, legal documents, and advertisements originating from Loudoun County and surrounding areas. They are organized chronologically.
The collection also contains a scrapbook of newspaper clippings chronicling Wilbur Hall's political activities, and two artifacts. There is a United States flag with 46 stars which belonged to General George C. Marshall and an undated "Christmas card" (a photograph of Wilbur Hall pasted onto a wooden stand).
The visual materials consist of sixteen photographs of various sizes and formats dating from 1866-1968. Photographs feature Wilbur Hall or were collected by him in the course of his research into a variety of historical topics. Organization of the photographs fall into two series: Series I consists of four folders containing photographs from research projects (speech or paper); Series II contains portrait images of Wilbur Hall.
Arrangement
Box: folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Alumni, Biographies, Wilbur C. Hall, http://law.wlu.edu/alumni/bios/hall-wilbur.asp (accessed 2 February 2012).
Wilbur C. Hall Papers (M 005), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Out of the Attic, Volume 2, February Birthday, 25 February 1982.
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect catalogue records
Contents List
- Manuscripts (Series I: Wilbur C. Hall Speech, Research and Correspondence Files)
  - A-Le
    - Alexander, Judge J. R. H.: Speech and correspondence, 1966-1967
    - American Legion "Miss Loudoun County" Speeches, nd (2)
    - Ball's Bluff Accounts: White, Col. E. V., History of the Battle of Ball's Bluff (nd); Notes on Ball's Bluff from Duyckinck, E.A., War for the Union, Vol. 2 (1861) 2pp, and "Remarks by J. D. Patch to The Leesburg Rotary Club," 14 May 1959, 7pp.
    - Ball's Bluff: Correspondence concerning a speech on Senator Edward Baker; the battle and battlefield, 1941, 1961 (14 letters)
    - Ball's Bluff Cemetery newsclipping: "Herald History from the Files of the Fairfax Herald: Ball's Bluff Cemetery," 25 October 1968
    - Ball's Bluff Maps: Maps of the Battle of Ball's Bluff (nd, compiler or publisher), 2 copies
    - Bedinger: Burning of Homestead, Gosport, VA, 1864, by Mrs. E. J. Lee of Shepherdstown, W VA, typescript, nd, 7pp.
    - Bridger, James: Biography (2 copies) and correspondence 1947-1948
    - Chamber of Commerce, Loudoun County, speech, handwritten notes and typescript, 1969
    - Champe, John: Speeches (2), votes and correspondence, 1954-1955; 1959-1967
    - Cooke, Philip St. George and the Mormon Battalion Memorial: Speeches, research, and correspondence, 1955-1956, 1967. (See VC0043 Box 1, Folder 2 for images of the Mormon Battalion Monument)
    - Democratic Committee and Loudoun County: Speeches (2), nd
    - Eaton, Mrs. John H. (Peggy O'Neal): Research notes and correspondence on birthplace, 1942 and 1955
    - Fauquier County: Speech, paper, and correspondence, 1940
    - Fauquier County Railroads: Photocopy of article "Southern Railway Has Seen a Lot of History Since the 1850s" by Harry A. deButts in The Fauquier Democrat 50th Anniversary edition, nd (ca. 1955)
    - Fox, George and "Devils Kitchen": Speech, Research and Correspondence, 1954
    - Fredericksburg: typescript of Civil War letter, 17 December 1862 and correspondence, 1949
    - General Assembly: Editorials (2), 1940 and nd
    - Greenup, Christopher: Speech and correspondence, 1959-1960
    - Hall, Stillson Hutchins: Memorials, 1981
    - Hall, Wilbur C.: Correspondence, documents, and legal papers, 1931-1968; Hummel, Jr., Ray O. and W. J. Barrow, Library Trends "Lamination and Other Methods of Restoration," January 1956; Loudoun Camp Meeting Association, Inc. certificate for shares, 1908
    - Hall, Wilbur C.: James Monroe Memorial Foundation Board appointment, 1960
    - Hall, Wilbur C.: Research notes on various topics, nd
    - Hall, Wilbur C.: Tree of Life, 1960 and portrait photographs (2) see VC0043, Folder 3 for portrait photographs of Wilbur C. Hall ca. 1934 and undated; see ART Box 1, item 1, Wilbur C. Hall "Christmas Card" (Photograph pasted onto wood cutout on wood stand), nd
    - Hunter, David (Major-General), typescript of 1864 Account of Burning Homes in Jefferson County, WVA, 4 pp.
    - Janney, John: Speech, research, and correspondence, 1938, 1961-1962; 1967-1968. See also VC0043, Folder 4: carte de visite John Janney, ca. 1866, inscribed and a group photograph of Lucas D. Phillips, Wilbur Hall (?) and Fred Howard
    - Jewell, William: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 1957-1961; see VC0043, Folder 5; images of William Jewell, Boone County Courthouse and Jewell Hall at William Jewell College, Liberty, Missouri
    - Lee, Ludwell, Speech, 1938, 16pp
    - Leesburg: Radio Talk (WJSV), speech, history, correspondence, research notes, and publication [The Town of Leesburg distributed by The Peoples National Bank of Leesburg, (2c)], 1944, 1963, and nd
    - Leesburg Business Directory, 1860, typed transcript and correspondence, 1963 and nd
  - Lo-R
    - Loudoun County: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 1942-1966
    - Tenth Annual Report of the Board of Directors of the Alexandria, Loudoun & Hampshire Rail Road Company for the Year Ending September 30, 1869 Made to the Stockholders in General Meeting, Held November 3, 1869. (Alexandria: Robert Bell Stationers, 1869, 16 pp with cover pp)
    - Loudoun National Bank: blank counter check, nd
    - Loudoun Times Publishing Company Situation Report, 1963
    - Loveless Murder, news clippings 1941
    - Lovettsville: research notes, nd
    - Marshall, George C: Tribute, resolutions, correspondence, and pamphlets, 1959-1969 (See also ART003 and VC0043)
    - Massey, "Parson" John E.: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 1942
    - Memorial Day: Speeches, research, and correspondence, 1967 and 1970
    - Mercer, Charles Fenton: Speeches, research notes, correspondence, Congressional Record Proceedings and debates of the 87th Congress, First Session, Vol 107 #22, February 6, 1961, and Abstract: Charles Fenton Mercer, 1778-1858 by Olliver O. Trumbo, 1937,1946, 1961, and nd
    - Monroe, James: Research materials in re Monroe's Congressional message of 2 December 1823 which became the Monroe Doctrine and Correspondence, 1940
    - Monroe, James: Speeches (4) and correspondence, 1943, 1952, 1957, and nd
    - The Plan of a Memorial for President James Monroe at "Oak Hill" Loudoun County, Virginia by James Monroe Foreign Service Educational Foundation, Aldie, VA, 1946
    - Monroe, James: Speech, research notes, Fishwick, Marshall W., "James Monroe of Oak Hill," and correspondence, 1960-1961
    - Mosby, John S.: Speech, research notes, photograph of Mosby, and certificate for John S. Mosby Sovereign Royal Council, 1877 and nd; see VC0043 Folder 7 for image of John S. Mosby and OM 019, folder 1 for Sovereign Royal Council certificate.
    - Neale, John Beckwith: Correspondence and research notes on birthplace, 1967; See VC0043 Folder 8 for image of Stonewall Jackson
    - Olive Branch Lodge (Masonic): History, remarks, correspondence, 1955-1968; see VC0043, Folder 9 group photograph (2) including Wilbur C. Hall
    - Public School System: Speech, research notes, publications: Hall, Wilbur C., The Future of Education in Virginia, Richmond, VA, 1930; Hall Wilbur C., "Representative Government At Its Worst in Virginia" reprinted from the Loudoun News, December 6, 1951; Remarks of Senator A. Willis Robertson Prepared for delivery at the Yorktown Victory Anniversary Celebration Sunday, October 19, 1958, Robertson, A. Willis, "Public Education in a Democracy," Congressional Records, 1961 (p. A323-4); Three Educational Address: Handicaps, Visions, and Talents, and Correspondence, 1930, 1951-1968
    - Rotary Club: Speeches, program, roster (1931), and correspondence, 1931-44, 1960, nd
  - S-W
    - State Commission on Conservation and Development (VA): Speech, 1936
    - Union Cemetery (Leesburg, VA): Speech (3 copies), 1946 and Act of Incorporation and Revised By-Laws of Union Cemetery, Leesburg, Virginia Incorporated February 27th 1852 (no publisher or publication date)
    - Washington, George: Speech, research notes, and correspondence, 1958-1959
    - Wayne, Anthony (Maj. Gen.): Speech, Research Notes, and Correspondence, 1941
- (Series II: Nineteenth Century Documents)
    - Broadside by SBT Caldwell to the Voters of Loudoun, 5 August 1831
    - Petition for appointment of George Mason as a midshipman, includes marginalia and 20 signatures, 18 Jan 1832
    - Lawsuit (copy) Christian Lanbower v Asa Rogers filed 11 June 1833, 7 p
    - Indenture, Samuel M. Edwards for James L. Martin for the benefit of creditors and John Norris, for the period 1837-1938, 24 August 1837, 6pp
    - ALS, Clinton to Mr. Connolly, re: transcontinental railroad and trade with the Pacific, 1 January 1849, 4pp
    - PFFI, court summons for John Martin, in Ramey v Harpers Ferry Savings Institution, 1 January 1849
    - ALS, Alfred P. Warfield, Waterford, VA to Asa Jackson, Leesburg, re Sons of Temperance 4 January 1849, 1p. Waterford Division N0 95 S of T St of VA, 15 February 1848
    - ALS, M. B. Perry, Gum Spring, VA to Thos. C. Connolly, Leesburg, re bid request for printing ballots for election of officers Gum Spring Sons of Temperance, 8 January 1849
    - ANS, request for special elections, John B. Floyd, Governor of Virginia, 17 April 1849 and Notice of special election for the House of Delegates, Loudoun County, Thomas Saunders, Sheriff of Loudoun County, 19 April 1849 2 documents attached
    - ANS, Runaway Slave Ad 26 [May] 1849, Henry B Tyler, Washington DC [May 2] 8, 1849, 1 p
    - ANS, Notice of Executors Sale of Negroes, Beverly Hutchinson, Executor for John Hutchins dec'd, 23 June 1849, 1 p
    - Virginia State Lotteries for the benefit of Monongalia Academy, June and December 1849
    - ADS, Notice of Commissioners sale of house and lot of land pursuant to a decree of the County Court of Loudoun pronounced on the 15 day of August 1849 in the case of Chas. W. Burke an infant v Mary Burke and Virginia E. Burke, signed by A. M. Vandevanter deputy for T. Saunders, Sherriff, 7 Sept 1849, 1 p
    - ANS, Notice for runaway slave ad, Thos. Foster and Wm Roach, Prince William County, 10 Sept 1849, 1 p
    - ANS, Advertisement for fruit trees, Yardley Taylor, 11 September 1849
    - ANS, Notice to collect debts owed to trustee, Robert L. T. White, 19 September 1849
    - ANS, Notices (2) for the dedication of the Loudoun Lodge # 26, IOOF, 6 October 1846, Thomas Littleton and Chas B. Tebbs
    - ANS, Advertisement for missing mare, L. M. Watkins, 14 October 1849, 1 p
    - ALS (3), Subscription renewal requests for the Chronicle, Leesburg, William Bradfield, P B Oden, and Emory & Co., 1849-1850
    - AN, Commissioner sale of Loudoun land, 22 January 1850, in the case of Solomon Crumbaker et al v Jacob Stoutsenberger surviving executor of John Stoutsenberger and executor Samuel Stoutsenberger, deceased, et al., 24 October 1849, 1p
    - ADS, in a Chancery Suit, Thomas Francis and Enoch Francis v Stephen McCarty and Elizabeth McCarty, his wife, John Francis, Edward Francis, William H Francis, and James Francis and William Francis, infant children of Lewis Francis dec'd and Fielding Littleton their guardian ad litem, Francis P. Knox, Clerk and F. W. Luckett, 24 October 1849, 1p
    - ANS (2) Administrators sale, land, negroes, stock of the estate of George Cuthbert Powell, Middleburg, 16 October 1849, B. P. Noland, Administrator, and Public Sale of Negroes, 17 December 1849, estate of Cuthbert Powell, William H. Gray and Charles S. Powell, executors, 6 December 1849
    - PF, Broadside Advertisement for Drugstore, Waterford, 12 April 1851; see OM 019, Folder 1
    - Advertisement: Bazaar in Aid of the Southern Prisoners' Relief Fund, Liverpool, 17 May 1864
    - The Centennial - balloon view of the grounds, Harpers Weekly 1876, see OM 019, folder 2
    - Johnstown, PA flood relief: Correspondence and Donor list, 1889
    - PFFI, Account of Mails received at the post office, undated and no place given, see OM 019, folder 3
    - ANS, advertisement for hiring out several valuable servant men, J. E. S. Hough; also for rent a dwelling on Cornwall St, JESH, Dec 31 ny, 1p
    - Folder 33 ANS, Notice of land for sale in the German Settlement, T. W. Edwards, nd, 1 p
  - S-W
    - Wilbur C. Hall Scrapbook, 1934-1935
    - Newspaper clippings on Hall's political activities
- Oversized Manuscripts
  - Mosby, John S. Sovereign Royal Council Certificate, 1877 (see also box 2, folder 15)
  - Broadside Advertisement for Drugstore, Waterford, VA, 12 April 1851 (see also box 3, folder 27)
  - The Centennial-balloon view of the grounds, Harpers Weekly, 1876 (see also box 3, folder 29)
  - Account of Mails received at the post office, undated and no place given (see also box 3, folder 31)
- Artifacts
  - United States flag with 46 stars belonging to George C. Marshall, nd
  - Wilbur C. Hall "Christmas Card" (Photograph pasted onto wood cutout on wood stand), nd
- Visual Collection
  - White, E. V
    - E. V. White, 35th Battalion, Virginia Calvary CSA., n.d. stamped "Philomont Civil War Exhibition, November 4, 1961" Copy
  - Mormon Battalion Monument in Sandoval County, New Mexico c.1956
    - Inscribed Tablet, oblique view. Kodachrome print
    - Inscribed Tablet, flat view Kodachrome print
    - Monument, Kodachrome print
    - Monument, Kodachrome print
    - Monument, Kodachrome print
    - View landscape near monument, highway. Sandoval County, New Mexico, Kodachrome print
  - Wilbur C Hall, Portraits
    - Wilbur Hall n.d. portrait in oval
    - Wilbur Hall, n.d. signed
  - Janney, John
    - John Janney, Carte de Visite c. 1866, inscribed
    - Group Photograph: Lucas Phillips, Wilbur Hall & Fred Howard at the Laurel Brigade Inn, n.d. 3x 5
  - Jewel, William (1789-1852)
    - William Jewell
    - Jewell Hall, William Jewell College, Liberty, MO
  - Marshall, George C.
    - George Marshall, n.d.
    - George Marshall, standing meeting with nine seated men, n.d. q stamped "National Geographic Society."
  - Mosby, John S.
    - Col. John S. Mosby, C.S.A. 43rd Battalion, VirginiaCalvary CSA n.d. stamped "Philomont Civil War Exhibition, November 4, 1961" Copy
  - Jackson, Stonewall
    - General Stonewall Jackson n.d. stamped "Philomont Civil War Exhibition November 4, 1961" (2 copies)
  - Rotary Meeting (Group Photograph)
    - Wilbur Hall, George Hammerly, William Hefner, unidentified man, at meeting (Rotary Club speech memorializing Marshall?) n.d. 8x 10
    - Wilbur Hall, George Hammerly, William Hefner, unidentified